Register to The Henry Gilbert Papers
Yale University Music Library
- Correspondence, 1858-1980; Series III; 4.6' (11 boxes)
  - Correspondence re Gilbert's Collaboration with Edward S. Curtis, III.G
    - Correspondence, 10 or more items. (Box 38, Folder 171-174)
      Includes correspondence from Charles Wakefield Cadman and Curtis among others.
  - Correspondence re New Music Society of America, III.H
    - Correspondence, 1906; 10 or more items. (Box 38, Folder 175-176)
      Includes letters from Chadwick, Converse, Goetschius, Goldmark, Charles Johnston, Edgar Stillman Kelley, Horatio Parker, Shepherd, and Stoeckel.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, III.I
    - Correspondence between others, 1890-1978; 10 or more items. (Box 38, Folder 177-178)
      Includes items from: Atherton, Chadwick, Downes, Farwell, Foote, Kahn, Marian MacDowell, Smallens, Spalding, and John B. Yeats (?).
    - Miscellaneous incomplete correspondence, no date (Box 38, Folder 179)
    - Letter of support of endowment for Gilbert, no date; 10 or more items. (Box 38, Folder 180)
      Signed by: Aldrich, Atherton, Carpenter, Clifton, Converse, Downes, Engel, Foote, Hale, Henderson, Hill, Victor Herbert, Kahn, Kelley, Liebling, Loeffler, Monteux, Osgood, H.T. Parker, Smith, Spalding, and Stransky.
- Clippings, 1845-1979; Series IV; 2.1' (5 boxes)
  This series is divided into the following sections:
  Miscellaneous clippings (arranged chronologically).
  Periodicals belonging to Henry Gilbert which contain articles by and about Henry Gilbert (arranged alphabetically by author).
  Entire periodicals belonging to Henry Gilbert retained although no direct link with Henry Gilbert has been found. These are arranged alphabetically by title on a list (2 p.) laid in folder 42/28.
  Clippings from miscellaneous periodicals (arranged chronologically). These include articles by Henry Gilbert which are listed alphabetically by title in the register.
  Transcriptions and excerpts from articles in newspapers and periodicals (arranged chronologically).
  See also: IX. WRITINGS. By Gilbert. Lectures and articles.
  The clippings have been copied onto acid-free paper.
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1845-1979; ca. 300 items. (Box 39, Folder 1-8)
  - Periodicals belonging to Henry Gilbert which contain articles by and about Henry Gilbert.
    The articles have been copied and the periodicals kept.
    See also: IX. WRITINGS. A. By Gilbert.
    - "When marriage fails," The World Tomorrow, Vol. X, pp. 274-77., 1927 Jun; Eubank, Earle Edward (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - "Society and American music." Atlantic Monthly, pp. 232-6., 1908 Feb; Farwell, Arthur, 1872-1952 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - "Johnny steps over Boston's threshold," Musical America, Vol. 48, p. 40., 1928 Dec 29; Gilbert, Elizabeth Yolande (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - "American composer," Musical Quarterly, Vol. I, pp. 169-80., 1915 Apr; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - "The curse of cleverness," The Gamut, Vol. I, pp. 34-5., 1928 Jun; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - "Folk-music in art-music - a discussion and a theory," Musical Quarterly, Vol. 3, pp. 577-601., 1917 Oct; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - "Humor in music," Musical Quarterly," Vol. 12, pp. 40-55., 1926 Jan; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - "Indian music," New Music Review, Vol. 11, pp. 56-9., 1912 Jan; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - "MacDowell Memorial Festival and Colony at Peterboro, New Hampshire," New Music Review, Vo. 11, pp. 461-3., 1912 Oct; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - "Notes on a trip to Frankfurt in the summer of 1927," Musical Quarterly, Vol. 16, pp. 21-37., 1930 Jan; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - "Originality," Musical Quarterly, Vol. 5, pp. 1-9., 1919 Jan; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - "Progress in art," Musical Quarterly, Vol. VI, pp. 159-74., 1920 Apr; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - "What is an American composer?," New Music Review, Vol. 22, pp. 449-452., 1923 Oct; Gilbert, Henry (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - "Henry F. Gilbert," Musical Courier, Vol. XCVI, p. 34., 1928 May (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - "Henry F. Gilbert's unfinished "Uncle Remus" opera," University of Texas at Austin. Department of Music and Institute of Latin American Studies. Yearbook, pp. 50-67., 1974; Longyear, Katherine E. and Rey M. (Box 41, Folder 22)
    - "American literature in American music," Musical Quarterly, Vol. XXXI, pp. 101-119., 1945 Jan; McGlinchee, Claire (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - "Henry F. Gilbert - conqueror," The Bostonian, Vol. I, pp. 19-20., 1928 Jul; McLain, Margaret Starr (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - "The American Musician," The Outlook, Vol. 109, pp. 341-5., 1915 Feb 10; Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1873-1953 (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - [Portrait of Henry Franklin Belknap Gilbert], Modern Music, Vol. XX, p. 218., 1943 May-Jun; Murray, Frank Waldo (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - "Sovietizing music in Russia," Musical America, Vol. 47, pp. 7, 48., 1928 Apr 14; Narodny, Ivan, 1869-1953 (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - "A troubadour of the new age," Musical America, Vol. 48, pp. 9, 30., 1928 Jun 16; Narodny, Ivan, 1869-1953 (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - The Village Gossip, 13 issues., 1910 Aug-Oct; Ney, Lou (Box 41, Folder 26)
      Note laid in.
    - "Again, Medusa," The Nation, Vol. CXXVIII, p. 192., 1929 Feb 13; Speyer, Leonora, 1872-1956 (Box 41, Folder 27)
  - Entire periodicals belonging to Henry Gilbert retained although no direct link with Henry Gilbert has been found. (Box 42, Folder 28-40)
    List is laid in folder 42/28.
  - Clippings from miscellaneous periodicals, 1898-1968; 45 items. (Box 43, Folder 41-45)
    Includes following articles by Henry Gilbert:
    - "American composer", 1915
      Annotated by Henry Gilbert.
    - "Americans don't know the meaning of art," Musical America, 1917 Mar 17
    - "Concerning jazz," New Music Review, no date
    - "Criticism," New Music Review, 1911
    - "Folk-music in art-music", 1917
    - "Humor in music", no date
    - "Musical hypocrites," New Music Review, 1921
    - "My summer in the movies," Musical Courier, 1923 Jan 18
    - "Note on folk song," Music Bulletin, no date
      Annotated by Henry Gilbert. Title changed from "Folk songs."
    - "On going to concerts," New Music Review, no date
    - "Originality," Musical Quarterly, 1919 Jan
      Proof copy annotated by Henry Gilbert.
    - "Personal collections of Edward MacDowell," New Music Review, no date
    - "Progress in art," Musical Quarterly, Vol. VI, 1920 Apr
    - "Survival of music", 1916
    - "What is an American composer?," New Music Review, 1923
  - Transcriptions and excerpts from articles in newspapers and periodicals, 1910-1932; 14 items. (Box 43, Folder 46)
- Programs, 1852-1976; Series V; .4' (1 box)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous programs, 1852-1976; ca. 102 items. (Box 44, Folder 1-12)
  - Program notes, no date; 6 items. (Box 44, Folder 13)
    Includes manuscript and typescript copies.
- Scrapbooks, 1852-1928; Series VI; 1.25' (3 boxes)
  Eight scrapbooks, the first six scrapbooks containing mostly clippings and programs, as well as correspondence and photographs. The correspondence and photographs have been removed and filed in the appropriate series. They are preserved in their original order on a microfilm made of the scrapbooks.
  The first six scrapbooks have been microfilmed, and the microfilm is housed in box 46. The remaining two scrapbooks are copied onto acid-free paper and the copies are laid in with the scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbook No. 1, 1913-1917; 61 p., bound; 30 cm. (Box 45)
  - Scrapbook No. 2, 1918-1920; 49 p., bound; 32 cm. (Box 45)
  - Scrapbook No. 3, 1920-1924; 5, [49] p., bound; 32 cm. (Box 45)
  - Scrapbook, 1922-1928; [76] p., bound; 32 cm. (Box 45)
    Loose items laid in.
  - Scrapbook [bird and spider on cover], 1886-1913; 99 p., bound; 28 cm. (Box 46)
    For original letters which include letters to Henry Gilbert from Bispharn (1906), Massenet, Ruggles (1908), and Shapleigh (1907), see: III. B.2. CORRESPONDENCE. To Gilbert. From others.
  - Scrapbook, 1852-1913; [46] p., bound; 26 cm. (Box 46)
    See also: XI. PHOTOGRAPHS.
  - New Haven: Yale University Photographic Services, 1982., 1852-1928; 1 microfilm reel: negative; 35 mm. (Box 46)
    Includes the above 6 scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbooks (Box 47)
    Two scrapbooks containing portraits and prints pasted in as well as annotations by Henry Gilbert. These have been photocopied and the copies are laid in.
    - "Miscellaneous Portraits", 29 leaves, bound; 29 cm.
    - Untitled scrapbook re Wagner, [26] leaves; 27 cm.
- Financial and Legal Items, 1829-1944; Series VII; .8' (2 boxes)
  This series is divided into five sections arranged chronologically except for Old stocks, which is arranged alphabetically.
  - Music copyrights, royalty statements, agreements, 1893-1968; ca. 202 items. (Box 48, Folder 1-12)
  - Legal documents, 1829-1941; 53 items. (Box 49, Folder 13-19)
    See also: VIII. MUSICAL GANES.
  - Old stocks, 1883-1933; 80 items. (Box 49, Folder 20-22)
  - Receipts, 1877-1944; 57 items. (Box 49, Folder 23)
  - Jottings in Henry Gilbert's hand as well as in other's hands, 14 items. (Box 49, Folder 24)
    Includes record in Henry Gilbert's hand of Edward S. Curtis account.
- Musical Games 2.1' (5 boxes), no date; Series VIII
  This series includes musical games invented by Gilbert, materials for making the games, and patents.
  - Musical Games by Henry Gilbert (Box 50; 51; 52; 53, Folder 1-4; 5-7; 8-9; 10-13)
    Including: Cross-tune puzzle, Melody (a game of musical solitaire), Melody building blocks, and musical card game.
    Unused blocks for "Music composition blocks," stamp for printing musical card games, and instructions for games.
    Mostly typescript and copies, 1 holograph sketch.
  - Patents (Box 54, Folder 14-17)
    By Henry Gilbert and others.
    See also: III. CORRESPONDENCE. A.2. From Gilbert, To others: Clyde Rogers, United States. Commissioner of Patents. B.2. To Gilbert, From others; Clyde Rogers, United States. Department of Commerce, United States Patent Office. C.2.; Between Mrs. Gilbert and others, To Mrs. Gilbert; James L. Edwards (1929 Apr).
- Writings, 1821-1928; Series IX; 6.7' (16 boxes)
  This series contains two subseries:
  A. Writings by Gilbert: Lectures and articles, Diaries and address books (arranged chronologically), Notebooks (arranged chronologically), Texts, synopses, and notes for Henry Gilbert's musical works, Minutes of the New Music Society of America (arranged chronologically), Chronological listing of composers and descriptions of their works, Notes re composers and their music, Miscellaneous jottings.
  B. Writings by Others: Librettos and scenarios (arranged alphabetically by author), Poetry (arranged alphabetically by author), Jottings by Mrs. Gilbert, Mrs. Horton, and others, Published or printed items belonging to Gilbert.
  Items containing markings, poetry, and school books have been retained. They are arranged alphabetically by author. The remaining items are arranged alphabetically by author in a list housed in box 64.
  - Writings by Gilbert, IX.A
    - Lectures and articles
      Arranged alphabetically.
      See also: IV. CLIPPINGS; Periodicals beloriging to Henry Gilbert which contain articles by and about Henry Gilbert; Clippings from miscellaneous periodicals.
      - American composer, 36 sheets; 20 cm. (Box 55, Folder 1)
        Holograph signed, and copy.
      - Art in America (Box 55, Folder 2)
        - Art in America, 6 p.; 28 cm.
          Typescript with pencil annotations by Henry Gilbert,
        - Art in America, 5 p.; 28 cm.
          Typescript (3 copies) with pencil annotations.
      - Art of music. 13, Musical examples
        See: Musical examples.
      - Basis of criticism, [29] p.; 23 cm. (Box 55, Folder 3)
      - Chapter of reminiscence (Box 55, Folder 4)
        - Chapter of reminiscence, 49 p.; 23 cm.
        - Chapter of reminiscence, 25 p.; 28 cm.
          Typescript with pencil annotations.
      - Characteristics of the folksongs of the different countries, 29 p.; 27 cm. (Box 55, Folder 5)
      - Chimera of democracy, [3], 6, 15, 20, 8, 7, 2 p.; 23 cm. (Box 55, Folder 6)
      - Composer and the public, 15 sheets; 23 cm. (Box 55, Folder 7)
      - Disease of harmony (Box 55, Folder 8)
        - Disease of harmony, 18 p.; 17-26 cm.
        - Disease of harmony, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
      - Endowment of the creative artist (Box 55, Folder 9)
        - Endowment of the creative artist, [12], [6], 29, [5] p.; 12-28 cm.
        - Endowment of the creative artist, [14] sheets; 28 cm.
      - Folk-music in art-music
        - Folk-music in art-music, 28, 55, 37, [5] p.; 23-28 cm. (Box 55, Folder 10)
        - Folk-music in art-music, 45 p.; 28 cm. (Box 55, Folder 11)
          Typescript with pencil and ink annotations and musical example pasted on.
      - Folksong, 13 leaves; 28 cm. (Box 55, Folder 12)
      - [Gogol], 5, [3] leaves; 17 cm. (Box 55, Folder 13)
      - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work (Box 55, Folder 14)
        - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work, [10] p.; 28 cm.
          Notes by Isolde Gilbert Horton laid in.
        - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work, 9 p.; 28 cm.
          "June 20-'23 OK" - p. 1.
        - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work, 9 p.; 28 cm.
          "OK. Jan. 1924" - p. 1.
        - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work, 8 p.; 28 cm.
      - Ideas of a composer (Box 55, Folder 15)
        Includes 2 contents pages and 5 essays (typescripts with annotations).
        - Midway plaisance music, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
        - Endowment of the creative artist, 14 sheets; 28 cm.
          Dated: 1908.
        - Disease of harmony, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
          Dated: 1919.
        - Music after the war, 13 p.; 28 cm.
        - Musical beginnings, 45 sheets; 28 cm.
          Musical examples pasted on.
      - [Marco Polo?], 34 p.; 28 cm. (Box 55, Folder 16)
        Typescript bibliography laid in.
      - Midway plaisance music (Box 55, Folder 17)
        Note by Isolde Gilbert Horton laid in.
        - Midway plaisance music, 8 sheets; 26 cm.
        - Midway plaisance music, [3] sheets; 28 cm.
          Manuscript in ink (pp. 1-2 are photocopies).
        - Midway plaisance music, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
          Typescript and photocopy.
      - Music after the war, 17 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 55, Folder 18)
      - Musical America, 24 p.; 27 cm. (Box 55, Folder 19)
      - Musical Examples: illustrating the progress of the art from the department editor Henry F. Gilbert. - New York National Society of Music, c1916., 378 p. of music, bound; 31 cm. (Box 56)
        Vol. 13 of the Art of music, edited by Daniel Gregory Mason, book I.
      - Musical hypocrites (Box 56, Folder 20)
        - Musical hypocrites, 14 p.; 20 cm.
        - Musical hypocrites, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
          Typescript (photocopies).
      - My summer in the movies, 17, [3] p.; 28 cm. (Box 56, Folder 21)
      - [North American Indian], [3] sheets; 28 cm. (Box 56, Folder 22)
        List laid in re Edward S. Curtis.
      - Note on the Indian music, pp. 165-66; 28 cm. (Box 56, Folder 23)
        Photocopy of the appendix to v. 6 of Curtis's North American Indian, added to the papers 1982 Dec.
      - Notes on a trip to Frankfurt in the summer of 1927 (Box 57, Folder 24-25)
        - Notes on a trip to Frankfurt in the summer of 1927, [8] p.; 26 cm.
        - Notes on a trip to Frankfurt in the summer of 1927, 12 sheets; 28 cm.
          Typescript (3 copies).
        - Notes on a trip to Frankfurt in the summer of 1927, 19 sheets; 28 cm.
          Typescript with pencil annotations by Henry Gilbert.
      - Notes on the "Suite for chamber orchestra", [3] p.; 28 cm. (Box 57, Folder 26)
        Typescript with holograph additions, signed.
      - Old man of the mountain, 10, [4j p.; 28 cm. (Box 57, Folder 27)
      - On going to concerts, 14, [6] p.; 15 x 22 cm. (Box 57, Folder 28)
        Holograph in pencil (and photocopy).
      - Orchestration, [24] p.; 27 cm. (Box 57, Folder 29)
      - Originality (Box 57, Folder 30)
        - Originality, 30 sheets; 20-23 cm.
        - Originality, 16 sheets; 28 cm.
      - Personalia, 19 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 57, Folder 31)
        Typescript (2 copies).
      - Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant (Box 57, Folder 32)
        - Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant, 64 [ie., 73] p.; 21 cm.
        - Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant, 24 sheets; 28 cm.
      - Possibilities of music, [4] p.; 20 cm. (Box 57, Folder 33)
      - Prayer of the modern composer, A-G sheets; 25 cm. (Box 57, Folder 34)
      - Primitive music
        - Primitive music, 107, [7] sheets; 26 cm. (Box 57, Folder 35)
        - Primitive music, [14] sheets; 60 cm. (Box 57, Folder 36)
          Proof sheets for Gilbert's chapter (I) in "The art of music."
          Contains annotations.
      - Problem of the American composer, 4 sheets; 14 x 21 cm. (Box 57, Folder 37)
        Also includes 3 more items.
      - Progress in art (Box 57, Folder 38)
        - Progress in art, [75] p.; 17-28 cm.
        - Progress in art, 33 sheets; 28 cm.
          Dated: ca. 1919-20.
      - Rube Hayseed goes to the circus (one-reel comedy filler) (Box 57, Folder 39)
        - Rube Hayseed goes to the circus (one-reel comedy filler), 6 p.; 28 cm.
        - Rube Hayseed goes to the circus (one-reel comedy filler), 1 sheet; 32 cm.
      - Schooldays past, 14, [1] p.; 15 x 22 cm. (Box 57, Folder 40)
      - Spirit of America, 8 p.; 26 cm. (Box 57, Folder 41)
      - Story of Mary Ellen (Box 57, Folder 42)
        - Story of Mary Ellen, 23 p.; 21-28 cm.
        - Story of Mary Ellen, 9 sheets; 28 cm.
      - Survival of music (Box 57, Folder 43)
        - Survival of music, 47 sheets; 21-32 cm.
        - Survival of music, 18 sheets; 28 cm.
          Typescript with ink corrections (2 copies).
      - Symphonic music in America, 29 sheets; 11-27 cm. (Box 57, Folder 44)
        Holograph signed, in pencil with ink-title page.
        Dated: ca. 1921 Sep.
      - [Wagner?], 35 sheets; 17 cm. (Box 57, Folder 45)
      - Waldo Murray
        - Waldo Murray, [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        - Waldo Murray, [1] sheet; 28 cm.
      - [What is an American composer?], [27] p.; 10-28 cm. (Box 57, Folder 46)
      - [What is jazz?], a1-6, b1-4, c1-2 p.; 20 cm. (Box 57, Folder 47)
        Holograph in pencil and photocopy.
      - Untitled items, 19 items. (Box 57, Folder 48-49)
        Holographs, photocopies, and typescripts.
    - Diaries and address books, 29 items. (Box 58)
      Dated: 1882-1928.
    - Notebooks, 1875-1927; 35 items. (Box 59; 60, Folder 50-62; 63-76)
      Including notes re: school, penmanship, thoughts and ideas, calculations, expenses, lists of compositions, music, natural history, minerals, and lepidopterology.
    - Texts, synopses, and notes for Henry Gilbert's musical works, Loose sheets ([114] p.). (Box 61, Folder 77-78)
      Holographs and typescripts.
    - Minutes of the New Music Society of America, 1905-1906; Loose sheets ([49] p.). (Box 61, Folder 79)
      Manuscript and holographs.
    - Chronological listing of composers and descriptions of their works, 78 cards. (Box 61, Folder 80)
    - Notes re composers and their music, 15 items. (Box 61, Folder 81)
    - Miscellaneous jottings, Loose sheets (ca. 850 p.). (Box 61; 62, Folder 82-97; 98-106)
      Holographs and some typescripts.
      Includes addressed but unmailed envelopes.
  - Writings by Others, IX.B
    - Librettos and scenarios
      Typescripts.
      See also: I.A. MUSIC. Opera and Incidental.
      - Gold in a penny: ballet-pantomime for three dancers and a mime., Humphrey, R.L.; 3 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 63, Folder 107)
        Typescript with annotations.
      - Lotelle and the make-believe lady: ballet pantomime for one dancer, Humphrey, R.L.; [1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 63, Folder 107)
        Dated: 1915.
      - Lily of ?, MacLaren, Donald; [8] sheets; 29 cm. (Box 63, Folder 108)
        Act IV, scenes I-II.
      - Girl of the fourth dimension, Narodny, Ivan, 1869-1953; 9 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 63, Folder 109)
        Typescript with ink annotations.
      - Merrymount: opera in three acts, Ranck, Edwin Carty (Box 63, Folder 110)
        - Libretto, 16, [21], [7] sheets; 28 cm.
          Typescript with annotations by Henry Gilbert.
        - Synopsis, 5, 6, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
      - Study for a musical comedy in one act to be called The Fortunes of Van Tassel., Robinson, Thomas P.; 50 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 63, Folder 111)
        Note on title page.
    - Poetry, Loose sheets (ca. 200 p.). (Box 63, Folder 112-119)
      Typescript and manuscript, some in Henry Gilbert's hand.
      Poetry by family and friends (includes holograph sonnet by Waldo Pierce).
      Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Jottings by Mrs. Gilbert, Mrs. Horton, and others, Notebook ([26] p.) and loose sheets ([56] p.). (Box 63, Folder 120-123)
      In pencil and ink.
    - Published or printed items belonging to Gilbert
      Items containing markings, as well as poetry and school books have been retained. The remaining items are arranged alphabetically by author in a list housed in box 64.
      - Scholar's arithmetic. - Keene, N.H.: John Prentiss, 1827., Adams, Daniel (Box 64)
      - Life of Samuel Johnson. - London: J. Richardson, 1821., Boswell, Janes
        5 v.
        Clippings, etc. have been pasted in. Copies of these are laid in folder 124.
      - Brief history of the United States. - New York; Chicago; New Orleans: A.S. Barnes, c1880. (Box 64, Folder 124)
      - Asra: miniature opera in one scene. - S.l.: s.n., c1925., Breil, Joseph Carl, 1870-1926 (Box 64, Folder 125)
        Libretto with musical sketch (by Henry Gilbert?) on p. 8.
      - Book of politeness. - Boston: Allen and Ticknor, 1833., Celnart, Mme.
      - Youth's gem. - Portland: S.H. Colesworthy, 1845., Clergyman
        Vol. I.
      - Intellectual arithmetic... - New York Hurd and Houghton: Boston: H.O. Houghton, 1863., Colburn, Warren
      - Theory and practice of musical form. - New York: G. Schirmer, 1883., Cornell, J.H. (Box 65)
      - North American Indian. - S.l.: Edward S. Curtis, 1917., Curtis, Edward S., 1868-1952 (Box 65, Folder 126)
        Introductory no., called also v.1.
      - Battles of the United States. - New York: Johnson, Fry, and Company, 1858., Dawson, Henry B.
      - Declaration of Independence; The constitution of the United States of America; The farewell address of George Washington; and The proclamation of General Jackson... / arranged by William W. Linfield. - Randolph, Mass.: Samuel P. Brown, 1862. (Box 65)
        Presentation card to Henry Gilbert laid in.
      - North American arithmetic. - Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott, 1856., Emerson, Frederick
      - A letter to American composers. - Newton Center, Mass.: Wa-Wan Press, 1903., Farwell, Arthur, 1872-1952 (Box 65, Folder 127)
      - Salammbô. - London: Vizetelly & Company, 1888., Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880
        Clipping (photocopy) laid in.
      - Indian games and dances with native songs. - Boston: C.C. Birchard, 1915., Fletcher, Alice G.
      - Gallo's band book. - Boston: Boston Music Company, c1921., Gallo, Stanislao (Box 65, Folder 128)
        Part I, wind instruments.
        Inscribed by the author, 1921 Aug 29.
      - Music of nature. - Boston: J.H. Wilkins & R.B. Carter, 1841., Gardiner, William, 1770-1853 (Box 66)
      - Complete arithmetic. - Boston: Robert S. Davis, c1881., Greenleaf, Benjamin
      - Guyot's new intermediate geography. - New York: Charles Scribner's, c1879.
      - Our world. - Boston: Ginn brothers, 1873., Hall, Mary L.
      - Handbook of the historic festival in Somerville, Massachusetts, November 28, 29, 30, December 1, 2, and 3, MDCCXCVIII. - [Somerville, Mass.]: s.n., 1898.